Imagine a T-shaped intersection.
T 字路の交差点を思い浮かべてみてください
The blue self-driving car pulls up to that stop sign and would
青い自動運転車が一時停止の標識で止まり 左折しようとしましたが
like to make a left turn but it sees this green car coming from the left.
緑の車が左側から来ています
If the green car is turning right,
緑の車が右折するのであれば
it is safe for the blue car to go.
青い車はそのまま進めます
But if the green car is going straight,
緑の車が直進すれば
then the blue car should wait.
青の車は待っていなければなりません
The way we would handle this with the model based approach is as follows.
モデルベースのアプローチでこれを処理する方法は 次のとおりです
First we would come up with two process models,
まずは 2 つのプロセスモデルが考えられます
one for going straight and one for turning right.
1 つは直進 もう 1 つは右折です
And we would use some simple trajectory generator to figure out
簡単なトラジェクトリージェネレータを使用して
what trajectory we would expect to see if
ドライバーが直進または右折した場合の
the driver were going straight or turning right.
トラジェクトリーを予測して把握します
Then we would pay attention to the actual behavior of the target vehicle and using
それから 目標車両の実際の動作に注目します
a multimodal estimation algorithm which is still a black box for now we would
マルチモーダル推定アルゴリズムを使用しますが ここではまだブラックボックスのままです
compare observed trajectory to the ones we would expect for each of our models.
観察されたトラジェクトリーと それぞれのモデルに対して予測されるトラジェクトリーを比較します
And then based on that we would
それに基づいて 考えられるトラジェクトリーそれぞれに
assign a probability to each of the possible trajectories.
確率を割り当てます
But the important takeaway for purely model based prediction is that we
純粋にモデルベースの予測に対して重要なポイントは
have some bank of possible behaviors and each has a mathematical model of
考えられる行動をひととおり用意して
motion which takes into account the physical capabilities of the object as well
それぞれのケースでオブジェクトの物理的機能を考慮したモーションの数学モデルと
as the constraints imposed by the road traffic laws and other restrictions.
道路交通法やその他の規制によって課せられた制約にも対応します
What about a data driven approach.
データ駆動型アプローチはどうでしょうか
Well with the purely data driven approach we have
純粋にデータ駆動型のアプローチでは
a truly blackbox algorithm and this algorithm will be trained on lots of training data.
本物のブラックボックスアルゴリズムと 多くのトレーニングデータで訓練したこのアルゴリズムを使用できます
Once it's trained we just fitted
トレーニングが完了すると 観察された行動が
the observed behavior and let it make a prediction about what will happen next.
適合され 次に何が起きるかの予測を立てることができます
So we can see that each approach has its own strengths.
こうしたアプローチには独自の強みがあることがわかりますね
Model based approaches incorporate our knowledge of
モデルベースのアプローチは 物理や道路交通法などによる
physics constraints imposed by the road traffic et cetera and
制約の知識が組み込まれ データ駆動型アプローチはデータを使用して
data driven approaches are nice because they let us use data to
モデルベースのアプローチでは見過ごしてしまいがちな
extract subtle patterns that would otherwise be missed by model based approaches.
難解なパターンを抽出できるのが利点です
For example differences in
たとえば 時間帯が異なると
vehicle behavior at an intersection during different times of the day.
交差点での車両行動にも差が出ます
And this leads to the somewhat leading question.
これは誘導尋問にもつながります
Which approach is the best.
最適なアプローチはどちらでしょうか